{"tossups": [{"question": "By defeating Eugenius at one of these locations in 394, Theodosius I quashed polytheism in favor of Christianity and briefly reunified the Roman Empire. Before a battle at another one of these geographical locations, the winning commander saw the phrase \u201cin hoc signo vinces\u201d in a dream, after which he painted the Chi-Rho [kye-roh] on his soldiers\u201d shields. Constantine I defeated Maxentius in a 312 AD battle at, for ten points, what type of geographical location, an Italian one of which is crossed by the Milvian Bridge?", "answer": "<b> river</b>s (accept<b> bridge</b> before read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This novel was composed during the volcanic winter after the eruption of Mount Tambora, which may have inspired the setting of a frame story in which Robert Walton meets the protagonist while exploring the North Pole. In this novel, Elizabeth Lavenza is killed on her wedding night after her husband refuses to create a female companion for his first creation. For ten points, name this novel about Victor, a mad scientist who creates life, written by Mary Shelley.", "answer": "<b> Frankenstein</b>; or, The Modern Prometheus", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This field\u2019s \u201cnew\u201d form combines it with ethnography and was developed by Lewis Binford. In a book that defined this field\u2019s \u201cprocessual\u201d form, Willey and Phillips claimed that it is \u201canthropology or it is nothing.\u201d The Harris Matrix outlines four \u201claws\u201d of this field, including the law of stratigraphic succession and the law of superposition. Practitioners of this field study sites like Skara Brae and Tel Megiddo. For ten points, name this field of study that examines artifacts and past human societies.", "answer": "<b> archaeology</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "This policy was enacted under the leadership of D.F. Mala and his National Party. In accordance with this policy, the movement of citizens were restricted by the Pass Laws. People protesting this policy were massacred at Sharpeville and Soweto. In 1993, F.W. de Klerk shared a Nobel Peace Prize for helping to end this policy. Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what South African system of racial segregation?", "answer": "<b> apartheid</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Using the method of<em> interpretatio romana</em>, Tacitus identified this god with Mercury in his<em> Germania</em>. One ceremony to this god involved hanging horses. This god, who was hung from the World Tree, sacrificed his eye for wisdom. This husband of Frigga rides the eight-legged horse Sleipnir and is the father of Balder and Thor. This god\u2019s German form is the namesake of Wednesday. For ten points, name this chief god of the Norse pantheon.", "answer": "<b> Odin</b> (accept<b> Wodan</b>; accept<b> Wuotan</b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This event was a consolation choice after proposals for it to be held at Egyptian pyramids, a Roman amphitheater in Tunisia at sunrise, or a cruise ship fell through. Michael Lindsay-Hogg filmed this event, which took place at 3 Savile Row and featured Billy Preston. This event, which included multiple takes of \u201cDon\u2019t Let Me Down\u201d and \u201cGet Back,\u201d was interrupted by police responding to noise complaints. The album<em> Let It Be</em> features songs recorded during, for ten points, what impromptu January 1969 event above London, the last time the Fab Four played live?", "answer": "the<b> Beatles\u201d rooftop concert</b> (prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptions of the Beatles\u201d last concert)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The United States organized the \u201ccoalition of the willing\u201d against this country after a report by an informant known as \u201cCurveball.\u201d A photograph of a man in this country wearing a hood and standing on a box was used as proof that American soldiers were abusing prisoners in Abu Ghraib. In 2003, the United States invaded this country to secure non-existent weapons of mass destruction. For ten points, name this country that was led by Saddam Hussein from Baghdad.", "answer": "<b> Iraq</b> (accept the<b> Iraq</b>i Republic)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This monarch introduced religious freedom in his kingdom with the Declaration of Indulgence, which was partially meant to protect his own Catholicism. George Jeffreys was appointed by this man to severely punish the instigators of the Monmouth Rebellion in the Bloody Assizes. This successor of Charles II served as the Stuart king before being replaced by the House of Orange. For ten points, name this King of England overthrown in the Glorious Revolution.", "answer": "<b> James II</b> of England (accept<b> James VI</b> of Scotland; prompt on James)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The McCone Commission investigated violence in this city, concluding that high unemployment and poor education led to a 1965 riot. Police in this city were accused of \u201ckicking a pregnant woman\u201d while arresting Marquette Frye and his family. In 1992, riots broke out in this city after four police officers were acquitted of beating an unarmed black man. The Watts and Rodney King Riots took place in, for ten points, what largest city in California?", "answer": "<b> Los Angeles</b> (accept<b> LA</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Treaty of Utrecht allowed this organization to build a depot in the English town of Lynn. The Victual Brothers temporarily seized a city dominated by this city in modern Gotland, the port of Visby. The Kingdom of Sweden weakened this organization by capturing ports in Pomerania and Prussia. For ten points, name this maritime league, largely made up of German city-states, that controlled Medieval Baltic trade.", "answer": "<b> Hanseatic</b> League", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This state\u2019s national guard once joined forces with this state\u2019s Fuel and Iron Company to attack a group of striking coal miners in what became known as the Ludlow Massacre. This state was home to the 59ers Gold Rush, which centered around Pike\u2019s Peak and fueled the growth of cities like Boulder and its capital, a \u201cMile High\u201d city. For ten points, name this western US state where miners built the city of Denver.", "answer": "<b> Colorado</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "King Salman and Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman lead, for ten points, what Middle Eastern country with capital Riyadh?", "answer": "<b> Saudi Arabia</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The 4th book of the<em> Continuations of the Chronicle of Fredegar</em> gives a biased account of this battle. This battle occurred after Odo the Great suffered multiple defeats at Narbonne and Bordeaux, leading his army to combine with Frankish forces. One side at this battle had no cavalry, opting to form the phalanx formation to combat Abd al-Rahman al-Ghafiqi\u2019s horses. For ten points, name this victory by Charles Martel that turned back the Muslim invasion of Europe.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tours</b> (accept Battle of<b> Poitier</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician responded to Harold Stassen\u2019s calls to ban the Communist Party by saying \u201cYou can\u2019t shoot an idea with a gun\u201d in the first Presidential debate to be broadcast on the radio. This politician prosecuted mob boss Lucky Luciano as a Special Prosecutor for Fiorello La Guardia before being elected Governor of New York in 1943. A photograph shows an opponent of this politician triumphantly holding a copy of the<em> Chicago Daily Tribune</em>. For ten points, name this politician who did not actually defeat Truman in the 1948 Presidential election.", "answer": "Thomas Edmund<b> Dewey</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A portrait of this man by Ingres [ahng] shows him seated on a throne while wearing a golden laurel. Jacques-Louis David [dah-VEED] painted numerous portraits of this man, including one at his study in the Tuileries [twee-luh-ree] Palace and another in which this man rides a rearing gray horse while crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor who was painted leading troops at the Battle of Waterloo.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon</b> Bonaparte (or<b> Napoleon</b> I)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>With Alexis Carrel, this man authored \u201cThe Culture of Organs,\u201d outlining the creation of an artificial heart. This man, at a dinner hosted by Hugh Wilson, controversially accepted</b> <b>the (+)</b> <b>Order of the German Eagle from Hermann Goring. A speech by this man, given</b> <b>Order of the German Eagle from Hermann Goring. A speech by this man, given</b> <b>on behalf of (*)</b> <b>on behalf of (*)</b> America First, claimed that the Roosevelt administration was a war agitator. The Orteig Prize was won by, for ten points, what pilot of the<em> Spirit of St. Louis</em>, an aviator who made the first nonstop solo flight across the Atlantic?", "answer": "Charles<b> Lindbergh</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Phillips Report, which detailed cost overruns for this project, was revealed to the</b> <b>public by Walter Mondale. Edward White, Roger (+)</b> <b>Chaffee, and Gus Grissom died</b> <b>Chaffee, and Gus Grissom died</b> <b>during an early phase of this program, which succeeded programs named (*)</b> <b>during an early phase of this program, which succeeded programs named (*)</b> <em>Mercury</em> and <em>Gemini</em>. On July 20, 1969, the Sea of Tranquility was the landing site of one of this project\u2019s modules, the <em>Eagle</em>. For ten points, name this project that sent the first astronauts to the Moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo</b> program (prompt on NASA and/or descriptions of the American space project)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In the prelude to this conflict, Lord Dalhousie flared tensions by annexing land under the Doctrine of Lapse. Soldiers in this conflict were shot out of cannons during particularly</b> <b>vicious fighting at (+)</b> <b>Cawnpore. Lucknow was besieged at the start of this conflict. This</b> <b>Cawnpore. Lucknow was besieged at the start of this conflict. This</b> <b>conflict was sparked after new (*)</b> <b>conflict was sparked after new (*)</b> cartridges for the Enfield rifle were allegedly greased with fat to offend both Muslim and Hindus soldiers. The British Raj was established in the aftermath of, for ten points, what 1857 revolt in India?", "answer": "<b> Sepoy</b> Mutiny (accept<b> Indian Revolt of 1857</b> before \u201cIndia\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This treaty led to a controversy over whether Mecklenburg had to concede more than the city of Wismar. A peace that this treaty failed to ensure was finally brokered in the</b> <b>Peace of Pyrenees. Swiss independence from the (+)</b> <b>Holy Roman Empire was formally</b> <b>established by this treaty, which also led the Dutch Republic to be formally recognized by (*)</b> Spain and reaffirmed the principles of the Peace of Augsburg. For ten points, name this treaty that was signed in Osnabruck and Munster and ended the Thirty Years War.", "answer": "Peace of<b> Westphalia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A division in this battle was positioned to cut off Confederate routes to Bethel Station. Nathan Bedford Forrest nearly died after ordering an attack through fallen timber in this</b> <b>battle. Future President James (+)</b> <b>Garfield fought on the second and final day of this</b> <b>battle under Don Carlos Buell. A line known as the Sunken Road was established around the key defensive position for the Union, which was called the (*) </b> Hornet\u2019s Nest. Cutting off the Memphis and Charleston Railroad was a central goal of, for ten points, what April 1862 Civil War battle in Tennessee?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Shiloh</b> (accept Battle of<b> Pittsburg Landing</b>) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This man justified himself to his enemies in the journal</b><em><b> Defender of the</b></em> <em><b>Constitution</b></em><b>. The Battle of Fleurus sped up the downfall of this man, provoking the Thermidorian Reaction against him. This promulgator of the Cult of the (+) Supreme Being accused his former ally, Georges Danton, of corruption and executed him; this man\u2019s own (*)</b> execution marked the end of the Reign of Terror. For ten points, name this \u201cincorruptible\u201d leader of the Committee of Public Safety during the French Revolution. ANSWER: Maximilien<b> Robespierre</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}